Today's דף daf is עין. Ayin. We pick up on the bottom
of ס"ט עמוד ב', Samech Tes amud bais, or the middle of
the bottom of ס"ט עמוד ב', Samech Tes amud bais, and we're
in the middle of a very famous אגדתא aggadata where the גמרא
Gemara is talking about the פסוקים pesukim in עזרא Ezra where it
says that they called out to God in a great cry. What
did they call out? And the גמרא Gemara says that they called
out that they're here, they're about to rebuild the second בית המקדש,
Bais Hamikdash, and they recognize that the first בית המקדש Bais Hamikdash
was destroyed because of עבודה זרה, avoda zara, and they're calling out
to God that this יצר הרע, yetzer hara, the evil inclination for
עבודה זרה, avoda zara, has led to all of this
terrible consequence and prayed to God to have it destroyed. And God
gave it over to them, and they put it in a lead
bowl or whatever pot, and they got rid of it. And then
they realized they wanted to do the same for the יצר הרע
yetzer hara of sex, but then they realized that that would be
too destructive, that the יצר yetzer of sex is what keeps procreation
going, keeps the world going, the power of the human drive and
so on.
So obviously quite fascinating, mostly people focus on the second part of
that about the יצר הרע yetzer hara of sex. I want to
just say one thing, one or two things about the יצר הרע
yetzer hara of עבודה זרה avoda zara before we continue. Number one
is, as I said, this has some
historical sort of חז"ל Chazal might have been looking
at when they described this at the historical reality, because as we
know, the גמרא Gemara says in the first בית המקדש Bais Hamikdash
was עבודה זרה, avoda zara, גילוי עריות, gilluy arayos, שפיכת דמים. shefichas
damim. Second בית המקדש, Bais Hamikdash, שנאת חינם. sinas chinam. And the
reality was in the time of the second בית המקדש, Bais Hamikdash,
if you read the נביאים, Nevi'im, all they're doing in the first
בית המקדש Bais Hamikdash is עוד העם מזבחים ומקטרים בבמות רק הבמות
לא סרו. od ha'am mezabbechim umekatterim babbamos rak habbamos lo soru. עבודה
זרה avoda zara is a huge thing. You don't hear about that
as a problem in the second בית המקדש Bais Hamikdash at all,
and the reality is in the larger world as well, there was
a waning of a serious sort of belief
in paganism and idolatry and so on. I mean, that was the
groundwork set for monotheistic faiths which has to do with Christianity and
so on. Anyway, so that's a reality that they are reflecting. Number
one, even though as I mentioned the פסוקים pesukim there in נחמיה
Nechemiah don't allude to עבודה זרה avoda zara at all, they allude
to the fact that they've regularly sinned in the past, but עבודה
זרה avoda zara is almost absent anyway, but that's I think partly
the issue that they are relating to, and the יצר yetzer they're
describing that this, how did this happen, because they prayed for the
destruction of the יצר הרע yetzer hara of עבודה זרה. avoda zara.
That's point number one. Point number two, though, is and the most
fascinating point is what is this that it emerged like a fire
of lion, a lion of fire from the קודש קודשים? Kodesh Kodashim?
What is the יצר הרע yetzer hara of עבודה זרה avoda zara
doing in the קודש קודשים Kodesh Kodashim as it were?
So there's different interpretations, but I think certainly the most immediate one
that it suggests is, we just read not so long ago in
the גמרא Gemara about a very iconic, that's probably the wrong word,
but physical manifestation of God and God's sort of connection to ישראל
Yisrael taking place in the קודש קודשים. Kodesh Kodashim. I mean, the
whole point that the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol enters into the קודש
קודשים Kodesh Kodashim
and that sort of led to this גמרא Gemara very much about
this erotic imagery of going into the inner chamber, and then the
discussion of the כרובים Keruvim and seeing the כרובים Keruvim intertwined, and
the גמרא Gemara says, like lovers,
and how this relates to how God and בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael
is shown to the בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael at the רגל, Regel,
but the כרובים Keruvim in general, it's an image. Now, it's not
the image of God, maybe it's the image of angels that surround
God or that are God's chariot. God is over the כרובים, Keruvim,
but it's a statue, it's physical, in the קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim,
in the holiest place which is the place of the most intense
presence of God. And on the one hand, obviously all of Judaism
is about getting rid of these images and how that corrupts the
idea of God, but there's this powerful human need for there to
be a way to directly connect in some ways that human beings
can relate to. So that was the עגל. Aygel. So you don't
have a representation of God, but a מקדש Mikdash you get stuff
that's a lot of
physicality without being God Godself, and you got the כרובים, Keruvim, which
again, not exactly God, but they're right there, they're right in the
קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, and they're actually these statues, and again, we're
right in the middle of talking about entering into the קודש קודשים
Kodesh Kodashim and this very intense encounter, and all of that imagery
about the כרובים Keruvim representing like I said, lovers and intertwined, and
that very, so that's a lot of stuff that feels a little
uncomfortable from a monotheistic getting rid of any images, any representation, very
pure type of a faith. But that also relates to this very
profound human need of this connection, which is a lot of the
physicality of the בית המקדש. Bais Hamikdash. So it could be that
what they're actually representing is that that... sort of, you know, there's
a יצר הרע Yetzer Hara of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah that's a
part of all of that desire of how to connect to God
in this physical way. You know, that's the same way the יצר
הרע Yetzer Hara of sex is not only bad, it's good, right?
It leads to marital sex and procreation and eggs and all of
these types of things. יצר העבודה זרה Yetzer Ha'avodah Zarah is this
desire for a more immediacy and intimacy of connection, and that is
that's part of what's going on in the קודש קודשים Kodesh Kodashim
in maybe a good way, but that's part of what's going on.
So if the יצר הרע Yetzer Hara of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
departs, right? Then it leaves the קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, then fine,
that's going to be a change in our way of relating to
God. And guess what also left the קודש קודשים Kodesh Kodashim in
the בית שני? Bayit Sheni? What didn't they have in the קודש
קודשים? Kodesh Kodashim? They didn't have the ארון Aron with the כרובים,
Keruvim, right? So they laid so that whole thing, that aspect of
our relating to God, which has a very negative side because of
how it can be completely, you know,
go off the דרך derech as it were and lead to a
real corruption of God, but there was also a power of that
connection as well, that departed. That they prayed for it to depart,
that left the קודש קודשים. Kodesh Kodashim. In that regard, I want
to read to you a fascinating like I give a lecture on
this side-by-side between a passage from רב קוק Rav Kook and a
passage from ישעיהו ליבוביץ. Yeshayahu Leibowitz. And I'm not going to read
the whole thing, but I want to just read you a section
because the basic פשט pshat is is that רב קוק Rav Kook
says, it's you know, the גמרא Gemara says that we lost the
יצר הרע Yetzer Hara of עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. רב קוק Rav
Kook says, it's too bad we lost the יצר הרע Yetzer Hara
of עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. That was the drive for a really
alive, passionate, immediate type of connection to God. Now the religion has
become sterile and dry and morose. That's what רב קוק Rav Kook
says.
ישעיהו ליבוביץ Yeshayahu Leibowitz says, you know the גמרא Gemara says we
lost the יצר הרע Yetzer Hara of עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah? Don't
believe it. That's just אגדתא. agadata. The יצר הרע Yetzer Hara of
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah is alive and well
in קבלה Kabbalah and in its followers and in רב קוק Rav
Kook and in his followers. And so this is like quite fascinating
how these two how they relate to. I'm just going to read
you one line from each. Hold on. It says,
he says like this. He says, he says now, you know, we
can have this from רב קוק Rav Kook from his it says
I'll give you the source. It's called אדר היקר. Adar HaYakar. Anyway,
he says that, you know, we used to have this very passionate,
alive, breathing religion, but it says אשר מאז שביטל יצרא דעבודה זרה,
asher me'az shebitel yitzra de'avodah zarah, but from the time that the
יצר הרע Yetzer Hara of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah has been has
been annulled, נסתלק כוח החיים הרענן שיסוד האהבה האלוקית מן העולם. nistalek
koach hachayim hara'anan sheyesod ha'ahava ha'elokit min ha'olam.
Departed the power, the life force of the sort of flourishing, you
know,
life force of the foundation of divine love from the world. כוח
אהבה אלוקית ככל כוח טבעי בלתי מעובד שבנפש האדם, צריך הוא ללימוד
של פיתוח וחיסון והדרכה. Koach ahava elokit kechol koach tiv'i bilti me'ubad
shebenefesh ha'adam, tzarich hu lelimud shel pituach vechissun vehadracha. He says, of
course, like any uncultivated power, you know, that we have, you need
it needs to be cultivated, it needs to be trained. You don't
cultivate it, right? And it goes wild and it goes off the
דרך derech and it leads to paganism and idolatry. The same with
the sexual desire. It has to be channeled, okay, but doesn't mean
you get rid of it. If you get rid of it, now
we don't have this passion and this love of God. And he
goes on and on about how because we've been amongst the other
nations, our religion has become shriveled and morose and so on and
we don't have this sort of the power for this really, you
know, emotional and immediate connection with God.
That's רב קוק. Rav Kook. And what ישעיהו ליבוביץ Yeshayahu Leibowitz in
a under the heading of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah in a in
a lexicon of Jewish ideas writes the following. Okay, he says like
this. He says, no,
no, I think it's his entry. He says האגדה מספרת שאנשי כנסת
הגדולה הצליחו להדביר את יצרא דעבודה זרה בישראל. Ha'agada mesaperet she'Anshei Knesset
HaGedolah hatzlichu lehadbir et yitzra de'avodah zarah beYisrael. The
האגדה ha'agada says that they succeeded in destroying the evil inclination. אך
אין אלה אלא דברי אגדה. Ach ein ele ela divrei agada. That's
just a story. מעולם לא פסק בעולמה של היהדות המאבק הנואש. Me'olam
lo pasak be'olama shel haYahadut hama'avak hanu'ash.
Never has ended in Judaism the the disheartening, you know, sort of
struggle של האמונה בה' אחד shel ha'emuna baHashem Echad with a belief
in a pure belief in a true God נגד המשיכה הטבעית של
האדם ובכלל זה גם האדם מישראל לאלילות neged hamshicha hativ'it shel ha'adam
ubechlal ze gam ha'adam miYisrael la'elilut against the natural inclination of a
person and
including Jews
for idolatry. אף מסווה של אמונה בה' אחד Af masveh shel emuna
baHashem Echad through a through a curtain of a belief of one
God, behind a mask of a belief of one God. כאשר האדם
הבדלה בין קודש לחול. Ka'asher ha'adam havdala bein kodesh lechol. People can't
deal with the difference between what's truly holy and truly transcendent and
something that's more of of their, you know, world. And he goes
on and he says whether this is talking about Christianity, whether this
is talking about קבלה. Kabbalah. And then finally, he says about he
gets in a lick at רב קוק. Rav Kook. He says,
he gets a lot of people in here, the כוזרי... Kuzari... the
המהר"ל, Maharal, okay, he says ועד לזמנים מזמנים בחסידות v'ad l'zmanim mizmanim
b'Chasidut through different parts of חסידות Chasidut ועד לרב קוק אשר בהגותו
עם ישראל v'ad l'Rav Kook asher b'haguto Am Yisrael etc.,
they've all turned into these physical manifestations of the divine. So, you
know, so really thinks about this tension, powerful tension, between a purity
of faith which is the rejection of imagery, right, but how impossible
or challenging that makes it to have a sense of a direct
connection to God? Because at the end of the day, we're physical
and we're human, so how do you connect to something that's completely
unlike you? So, you know, so that is, you know, is it
a good thing or a bad thing that we lost it? But
this אגדתא Agadata is describing that there was a profound change in
the time of the בית שני Bayit Sheini and again, fascinating how
it locates that it left from the קודש קדשים Kodesh Kadashim considering
everything that we've discussed about that encounter in the קודש קדשים Kodesh
Kadashim and how in the בית שני Bayit Sheini you no longer
had the כרובים Keruvim and the ארון, Aron, you just have the
stone.
Yes, רב קוק Rav Kook is saying that the rabbis at the
time erred.
I don't know. You could read, he doesn't exactly say that, but
yes, he says it's too bad that we've lost it. He might
have said that it was needed at that time because of how
it had gone so out of control. Remember they didn't kill it,
they just put it in a lead pot. Maybe saying we now
gotta let it go out of the pot again. Maybe we'll blind
its eyes like we did with the יצר הרע Yetzer Hara for
sex, but we still gotta let it back out of the pot.
So maybe instead of looking for the side of the ארון, Aron,
we should be looking for the inside of the lead pot.
Very good. What? They're buried together.
They're buried together.
I mean about the the the I don't know about the lion.
Okay, let's get back to the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara says
like this.
Yes, the whole construct is also extremely Greek in the tension between
the Apollonian tension and Dionysian tension. The Greeks had the same tension,
that the human being has deep within them a Dionysian impulse for
pure non-rational passion which needs to be bridled by what Apollo represented
in terms of the rational. That's interesting. You have a Dionysian ceremony
every
week.
Right, right, right. So that's emphasizing sort of the very the passionate
aspect which is definitely a part of this, but I don't want
to forget that even taking away sort of the senses component of
it, you know, there's still this desire to connect and the impossibility
of connecting with something that is completely other. So you know, so
yes, but yes, definitely the whole senses aspect and the passion is
a major part of that. Okay, let's get back to the גמרא.
Gemara. It says, okay, במערבא מתנו הכי. b'ma'arava matnu hachi. רב גידל,
Rav Gidel, the line starts with the word אמר. amar. It is
about 20 lines from the bottom, there's a little ה Heh in
parentheses one word in after the word אמר. amar. So in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael they teach the following. רב גידל אמר, Rav Gidel
amar, גדול, gadol, what does it mean that the with a with
you know that the the great God talking about that event in
עזרא Ezra of the reading of the תורה? Torah? שגדלו בשם המפורש.
she'gidlo b'shem hamiforash. Like we said before that they used God's ineffable
name when they read the תורה Torah at this gathering, you know,
at the in the with עזרא. Ezra. רב מתנא אמר, Rav Matna
amar, רב מתנא Rav Matna says, האל הגדול הגבור והנורא. ha'Eil hagadol
hagibor v'hanora.
No, what they did was this other פסוק pasuk in נחמיה Nechemia
when they praised God and they used the words גדול, gadol, again,
all of this is a discussion of what this word גדול gadol
meant. Did they use God's name, did they give a blessing to
God? So he says it's how they describe God. God who is
great and powerful and awesome, full of awe. והא דרב מתנא, v'ha
d'Rav Matna, now this statement of רב מתנא Rav Matna that they
underscored that this was what was so special about what they did
at this reading of the תורה Torah that they used this character
these words to describe God, so מטיא לדרבי יהושע בן לוי, matya
l'd'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, sort of inclines towards, is similar to a
statement of רבי יהושע בן לוי. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. דאמר רבי
יהושע בן לוי, d'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, רבי יהושע בן לוי
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi says, למה נקרא שמם אנשי כנסת הגדולה? lama
nikra shemam Anshei Knesset HaGedolah?
Why were they the people who were so seen as the forerunners
of חז"ל Chazal and beginning in the beginning of the בית שני
Bayit Sheini period, the members of the Great Assembly, the ones who
were מתקין תפילה metakin tefillah according to חז"ל Chazal and so on,
did many of these sort of early institutions of Judaism in the
בית שני Bayit Sheini period, why were they called people of the
Great Assembly? What's great,
גדולה? Gedolah? שהחזירו עטרה ליושנה, she'hechziru atarah l'yoshnah, they returned the crown
to its old glory. What does that mean? The crown had been
dirtied or whatever had had lost its shine. אתא משה ואמר, ata
Moshe v'amar, when משה Moshe was around he said, האל הגדול הגבור
והנורא. ha'Eil hagadol hagibor v'hanora. He described God as great, powerful, and
full of awe. אתא ירמיה, ata Yirmeyahu, but ירמיה Yirmeyahu came and
when it was like, you know, and the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
was destroyed, ואמר, v'amar, and he said, נכרים מקרקרים בהיכלו, nochrim mekarkrim
b'heichalo, the non-Jews are
dancing or croaking, yeah there's different גרסאות girsas some have מרקדין, mirkadin,
in God's sanctuary. איה נוראותיו? ayeh nora'otav? Where is God's awe that
they feel they have license to do this? לא אמר נורא, lo
amar nora, he didn't say נורא, nora, because if you look in
a פסוק pasuk in ירמיה, Yirmeyahu, it says האל הגדול הגבור. ha'Eil
hagadol hagibor. He didn't say נורא. Nora. רש"י Rashi I think quotes
the פסוק. Pasuk. רש"י Rashi says, yeah, רש"י Rashi says, האל הגדול
והגיבור ה' צבאות שמו, HaEil HaGadol VeHaGibor Hashem Tzeva'os Shmo, ירמיהו ל"ב.
Yirmiyahu Lamed-Beis. He didn't say נורא. Nora. He couldn't say נורא. Nora.
He couldn't bring himself to say נורא. Nora.
אתא דניאל. Ata Daniel. דניאל, Daniel, what, they were already in גלות,
Galus, came and אמר, amar, נוכרים משתעבדים בבניו. Nochrim mishta'abdim bevanav. Look
what's happening here in גלות. Galus. Non-Jews are subjugating God's children, we're
under the yoke of the
Babylonians. איה גבורותיו? Ayey Gevurosav? Where is God's power and might? You
don't subjugate somebody
else's children if you're afraid of their
power. לא אמר גיבור Lo amar Gibor because the פסוק Pasuk in
דניאל Daniel says, says האל הגדול והנורא. HaEil HaGadol VeHaNora. It does
not say גיבור. Gibor.
He just says הגדול והנורא.
HaGadol VeHaNora. Okay, whatever. אתו אינהו Asu Inhu and אמרו, amru, so
they came along and they said, no, אדרבה, adaraba, the opposite is
true. זו היא גבורה, Zu hi gevura, זו היא גבורתו, zu hi
gevuraso, שכובש את יצרו. shekovesh es yitzro. This is how God shows
His power, that He's able to subjugate His desire, right? איזהו גיבור
הכובש את יצרו. Eizehu Gibor hakovesh es yitzro. שנותן, Shemosein, and He
doesn't act, He's
not, doesn't have poor impulse control, He doesn't act immediately. שנותן ארך
אפים לרשעים. Shemosein erech apayim lareshaim. He lets the wicked get away
with stuff, not ultimately, but He does not immediately react, and that's
His greatness. Maybe He gives people opportunity to do תשובה. teshuvah. He
gives sinners an opportunity to get deeper into their hole, maybe, but
He allows people free will and that's God's greatness. ואלו נוראותיו, Ve'elu
nora'osav, and that's also God's awesomeness. שאילמלי מוראו של הקדוש ברוך הוא,
She'ilmaley mora'osho shel HaKadosh Baruch Hu, if it were not that there
was this fear of God, היך אומה אחת יכולה להתקיים בין האומות?
heich u'umah achas yachola lehiskayaim bein ha'umos? How could we have survived
such a long גלות? Galus? We're a tiny little people, we're amongst
these huge nations. At some level, there was some awe and fear
of God and of the Jewish people that has not allowed us
to be completely destroyed, so even with all these bad things happening.
So that's what the אנשי כנסת הגדולה Anshei Kenesses HaGidola
because, it's quite fascinating by the way, because the one word that
wasn't taken out by ירמיהו Yirmiyahu and דניאל Daniel was גדול. Gadol.
They didn't have to get the word גדול Gadol to go back,
but anyway, they restored the other words and that was their greatness
and that's what you see therefore when in the time of עזרא
Ezra he uses all three terms: האל הגדול הגיבור והנורא. HaEil HaGadol
HaGibor VeHaNora. So now the גמרא Gemara isn't done. The גמרא Gemara
says, ורבנן היכי עבדי הכי ואקרי תקנתא דתקן משה? Verabbanan heichy avid
hachi ve'akri takanta detakan Moshe? How did the Rabbis, funny who's being
called Rabbis, but ירמיהו Yirmiyahu and דניאל, Daniel, how did they take
away one of the words used to describe God? I mean, it's
in the תורה. Torah. What allows you to change what's in the,
it's not like there's a מצוה mitzvah to use those three terms,
but it's an institution, a way of talking about God that משה
Moshe established with these terms, where do you get the חוצפה chutzpah
taking one of those terms out? אמר רבי אלעזר מתוך שיודעין בהקדוש
ברוך הוא שאמיתי הוא, Amar Rabbi Elazar mitoch sheyodein baHakadosh Baruch Hu
she'amiti hu, because they know ultimately God is about truth. Remember when
they prayed for the יצר yetzer of עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, the
little פתק petek of אמת emes fell from heaven. So they know
that God is about truth, לפיכך לא כיזבו בו. lefikach lo kizvu
bo. If God is all about truth, we're not going to lie
when we're talking about God. You have to be true to our
experience of God. Now the מהרש"א Maharsha says it doesn't חס ושלום
chas veshalom mean that משה Moshe got it wrong. It means obviously
God is האל הגדול הגיבור והנורא, HaEil HaGadol HaGibor VeHaNora, but that
they, God was not demonstrating that aspect of who God was in
their time. That truth that is true about God but that wasn't
being manifested about God in their time, and they could not say
something about God that was not true to their experience of God.
So this passage is extremely powerful, I when I talking to people
about when they have challenges in terms of liturgy because that's ultimately
what it is. How do you say things in the liturgy that
you don't feel are true, true to at least your religious experience
of God, your religious
reality? How do you say things that you don't connect
to? And some people, I'll just tell you one way, about back
when I first came to Riverdale, must have been about 15 years
ago or so, one of the early sermons I remember Rabbi Weiss
giving was all about how we have to have more כוונה kavanah
in דאבנינג. davening. And then afterwards he comes over a week later
I bump into him and he said I got a letter from
somebody about my sermon. He said nobody ever says anything to me
about my sermon, but somebody actually wrote a letter. And he says
and in this letter this person said Rabbi Weiss, please don't ask
me to have more כוונה kavanah in דאבנינג. davening. The only way
I survive דאבנינג davening is by not having כוונה. kavanah. And
that this person was basically saying if I try to have כוונה
kavanah there are too many things that I don't feel
aligned with. So what do I do when those words don't resonate
and don't feel true to me? So one approach is don't have
כוונה. kavanah. I guess one approach is change the דאבנינג. davening. There
are definitely
denominations and people that modify the דאבנינג davening to take out the
things that they don't
feel. you don't change the words, you well you re-interpret them. Right,
that's the classic תורה שבעל פה Torah she-ba'al peh approach is that
you interpret and you re-interpret and you find a way, you know,
to make them be meaningful for your experience. It's like called a,
there's a phrase like as like, also called like trans-valuing, which is
it's not you maintain the practice, but you find a way in
which to give it value and meaning in a way in which
it sort of resonates and remains to be true to you if
you frame it in a different way. And that's really about the,
you know, the tension between maintaining the tradition and maintaining the continuity
and, you know, and not everybody sort of do it like a
make it yourself type of a thing, but still recognizing that importance
of being true to yourself and true to God and how do
you bridge that? So a very powerful גמרא Gemara in that
regard. And so, again, I don't know if that fits into a
larger theme we're talking about now about יום כיפור Yom Kippur or
about the earlier theme about the יצר הרע yetzer hara of עבודה
זרה avodah zarah but two very powerful אגדתות aggadotot right here on
this דף. daf. Okay, and now back to the regular עבודה avodah
of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Okay, וקרא אחרי מות ואך בעשור. V'kara
acharei mot v'ach be-asor. So the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is there.
He's now in the עזרה azarah or maybe in the עזרת נשים
ezrat nashim we said, and he's reading from the תורה Torah and
he's doing a, you know, what are you doing on יום טוב
Yom Tov and on שבת Shabbos or whatever? You read the תורה.
Torah. So he reads the פרשה parsha of אחרי מות Acharei Mot
which is the עבודה avodah and אך בעשור Ach Asor which is
later, which is in אמור, Emor, which is the מוסף. Musaf. So
the גמרא Gemara says רמינהי, raminhu, hi, I'll ask you on this:
מדלגין בנביא ואין מדלגין בתורה. m'dalgin b'Navi v'ein m'dalgin b'Torah. You can
skip when you're reading נביא, Navi, the הפטרה, haftarah, you can skip
from one section to the next but not when you're reading the
תורה. Torah. So how can in one reading he scroll a little
bit and jump פסוקים pesukim and read from a different section?
What does it mean to מדלגין? m'dalgin?
Do they mean like patch and paste פסוקים? pesukim? As in some
הפטרות haftarot we jump like twenty פסוקים pesukim later and end the
הפטרה haftarah with a פסוק pasuk that's not continuous?
We've done it in a טורח ציבור torach tzibur now.
Right, scroll a whole column. Right, for the הפטרה.
haftarah. No, no, what are you talking about? What are you talking
about?
We scroll a whole column forward. We skip a whole column between
the first and second.
Oh, that's true. That's true. So
well we'll see because this because the גמרא Gemara particularly, well let's
see how the גמרא Gemara qualifies it, okay? Let's see how the
גמרא Gemara qualifies it, because now it's saying you don't do it.
One of the differences there anyway could be that that's different עליות
aliyot and we're going to get to the issue of different עליות
aliyot in a minute, different people being called up which allows you
on a separate another person you could go somewhere else.
Right, but
here, but in a מפטיר maftir you don't. Sometimes in a מפטיר
maftir you start one thing and then you jump פסוקים pesukim or
you, you know, and you read from a different section. So מדלגין
בנביא, m'dalgin b'Navi, you can jump when you're reading נביא Navi in
the הפטרה haftarah even with one person. The point about the, about
the טורח ציבור torach tzibur is good,
but that's two different עליות. aliyot. But here we're talking even within
one עליה, aliya, you jump in the הפטרה haftarah ואין מדלגין בתורה,
v'ein m'dalgin b'Torah, you do not jump when you're reading the תורה.
Torah. So how could the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol jump? לא קשיא:
lo kashya: כאן בכדי שיפסיק התורגמן כאן בכדי שלא יפסיק התורגמן. kan
b'kdei she-yafsik ha-turgeman kan b'kdei she-lo yafsik ha-turgeman. Can you scroll and
jump to the new place before the תורגמן turgeman finishes doing his
translation? So you don't want to, yeah, this takes back to the
translators. Right. Right. Anyway, do you, so do, if you can do
it before the, so you don't have to have an obvious pause,
it's like he finished and wait wait I haven't got up to
it yet, then that's a problem, you know. But if you can
do it without an obvious pause, as soon as he's finished you're
already up to the new place, then it's okay, which is quite
fascinating, which locates the problem in being the pause and the waiting
and the interruption, whereas you might have thought the problem is, is
that you don't want people to think that, you know, by a
תורה Torah it's much more important for them to understand the flow
of the פסוקים pesukim and not to think that these פסוקים pesukim
are juxtaposed. You know, with a נביא, Navi, maybe that's not as
critical of a concern. So here it's saying no actually if you
can do it without a pause you're okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says והא לק תני, v'ha lakh tani, one minute, but on that
we actually said, on this, on this ברייתא, baraita, we said מדלגין
בנביא ואין מדלגין בתורה, m'dalgin b'Navi v'ein m'dalgin b'Torah, you skip in
the נביא, Navi, not the תורה. Torah. ועד כמה מדלגין? v'ad kama
m'dalgin? How much can you skip when you're allowed to skip in
the נביא? Navi? בכדי שלא יפסיק התורגמן. b'kdei she-lo yafsik ha-turgeman.
So when you're allowed to skip in the נביא Navi that's as
long as you do it without the guy interrupting, that's as long
as you don't have to pause. הא בתורה, ha b'Torah, so it's
clear that regarding the תורה, Torah, כלל כלל לא, klal klal lo,
even if the guy doesn't have to pause, even if you don't
have to pause, even if you could do it quickly, you're not
allowed to skip. אמר אביי, amar Abaye, said אביי, Abaye, לא קשיא
lo kashya it's not difficult: כאן בעניין אחד כאן בשני עניינים. kan
b'inyan echad kan b'shnei inyanim. It depends whether it's a different topic.
You can't, if you're in the middle of reading, you know, a
story of אברהם, Avraham, you don't skip to a story of יעקב,
Yaakov, right? But if you're reading the passage about the עבודה avodah
of יום כיפור Yom Kippur of אחרי מות, Acharei Mot, then you
can go ahead and skip to אמור Emor and read the מוסף
Musaf because then you're maintaining the theme. But again then it seems
like the problem is not that people will leave with an impression
that this is the order of the פסוקים. pesukim. פסוקים pesukim *Pesukim*,
that's not—is that the problem? Who cares? One topic, two topics? If
anything, you're more likely to think that it's all one thing if
they are of the same theme, right? So what exactly is the
problem? So if you look at רשי Rashi *Rashi*, רשי Rashi, *Rashi*
says בנין אחד *Binyan echad* of that 10 lines from the bottom,
כגון הכא ששתי הפרשיות מדברות בענין יום הכיפורים מדלגין *Kegon hacha she-shtei
haparshiyot midabrot b'inyan Yom HaKippurim medalguim*, ובכדי שלא יפסיק התורגמן *uvichdei shelo
yafsik hatorgeman*, and you also have to make sure that you can
jump, you need both things, right? If it's the תורה Torah *Torah*,
that the guy—that the guy hasn't finished interpreting and that it's the
same topic. הא דתניא דאפילו בכדי שלא יפסיק נמי לא ידלג בשני
עניינים *Ha d'tanya d'afillu bichdei shelo yafsik nami lo yedaleg bishnei inyanim*,
what's the issue of two separate topics? לפי שדברי תורה Torah. היא
עטרות ועונשים ומצוות *L'fi shediveri Torah hi atarot v'onashim u'mitzvot*, okay, that
the תורה Torah, *Torah*'s really very weighty, right? Every single פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* is about what you can do and can't do and consequences,
וצריכים שיכנסו בלב השומעים *v'tzrichim sheyikansu be-lev hashomim*, and you have to
absorb it, right? It's a great—interesting—a similar—just words, right? Enter into the
heart to absorb, you have to absorb what you're hearing. וכשהאדם יוצא
משיטה לשיטה אחרת אינו נוח לפניו *uchshe-ha'adam yotze me-shitta le-shitta acheret eino
no'ach lefanav*, if you're jumping around different topics and different ideas, it's
way too confusing. I can't absorb everything I'm hearing. So according to
רשי Rashi *Rashi*, the problem is not that you might believe that
this is all one פרשה parsha *parsha*. You might actually—you might actually
believe that, but we're okay with that. We just want to make
sure that if you're listening to the תורה Torah? *Torah*, you're getting
everything that you're hearing, that you're able to absorb everything you're hearing.
Fascinating way of explaining where the locus of our concern is. Okay,
I don't know. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Okay,
the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says ותניא *v'tanya* and we taught similarly in
a ברייתא *braita*, מדלגים בתורה בענין אחד *medalguim ba-Torah b'inyan echad*, in
the תורה Torah, *Torah* you can jump if you're sticking within the
same theme, ובנביא בשני עניינים *u'vi-Navi bishnei inyanim*, and by a נביא
*Navi* you can even jump from one theme to the next. וכאן
וכאן *V'chan v'chan*, and in both cases, what's necessary is ובכדי שלא
יפסיק התורגמן *uvichdei shelo yafsik hatorgeman*, and you do it before the
translator finishes so there's no pause. Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara*
says ואין מדלגים מנביא לנביא *v'ein medalguim mi-Navi le-Navi*, I'm sorry, keep
it going, ובנביא של שנים עשר מדלגים *u'vi-Navi shel Shneim Asar medalguim*.
What you can't do is you can't jump from one נביא *Navi*
to the next. Don't begin reading in ירמיה *Yirmeyahu* and then jump
to something in ישעיהו *Yeshayahu*. But you can jump from שנים עשר
*Shneim Asar*, which is quite fascinating because you know, there's like—which we
do, actually, right around the ימים נוראים *Yamim Noraim*, right? We have
מיכה *Micha*, we add it in to the whole thing of שבת
Shabbos. שובה *Shabbat Shuva*, right? Which is fascinating. They're different authors, but
sometimes it's halachically the same ספר sefer *Sefer*. We're allowed to jump
around. ובלבד שלא ידלג מסוף הספר לתחילתו *Uvilvad shelo yedaleg mi-sof hasefer
l'tchilato*. The one thing you can't do is don't go backwards in
the same ספר sefer *Sefer*. So right, you could start like by
נביא *Navi* number 11 of the שנים עשר *Shneim Asar*, presumably, and
jump to number 10 maybe, but not necessarily, because it says—I actually
don't know, I have to check that out. I'm not sure that
within one ספר *Sefer*, that's considered one ספר *Sefer*, that what gives
you the latitude to jump. So what do we do, actually, when
we do it on שבת שובה *Shabbat Shuva*? We jump from what
to what?
From הושע *Hoshea*—you can look
over there, rabbi, there's a חומש *Chumash* right there. Is that—is that—by
שבת
שובה *Shabbat Shuva* we jump from—there's three different פסוקים pesukim.
*Pesukim*.
Well, there's different customs, but
they're—we only did two here. I didn't realize that the הפטורות *Haftarot*
were—anyway.
We jump,
okay, we jump הושע *Hoshea*, יואל *Yoel*, מיכה *Micha*. Now who knows
the order of תרי עשר *Trei Asar*? Is that keeping in the
order? הושע *Hoshea*, יואל *Yoel*, מיכה *Micha*? Say it again?
הושע *Hoshea* comes before מיכה *Micha*.
And יואל *Yoel*?
No, יואל *Yoel* I think is after מיכה *Micha*, I think. Really?
Okay, so somebody can check that. Anyway, the one thing you don't
do is you don't go backwards. Okay, so maybe that takes—a different
story.
Yeah, but—but what allows us to jump from one נביא *Navi* to
the next is it's the same ספר *Sefer*. Okay, moving on.
הושע *Hoshea*, יואל *Yoel*, מיכה *Micha*.
Is that the right order?
Yeah, and there's a few in between יואל *Yoel*.
But that is sequential. There you go, so that's sequential. Okay, all
right, moving on. וגולל ספר תורה Sefer Torah. *V'golel Sefer Torah*. Okay,
so he reads, then he rolls up the ספר תורה Sefer Torah
*Sefer Torah*, holds it, and then he reads the part that's in
פנחס *Pinchas* בעל פה *b'al peh*. And he says, 'More than is
written here, I—you know, more—you know, more is written here than I've
actually read to you,' so that they understand that he's reading—I'll get
you the exact language. He says—he reads it, he rolls it up,
puts it in his chest, and says יתיר ממה שקראתי לפניכם כתוב
כאן *Yatir mima shekarati lifneichem katuv kan*, 'More than is written in
here is—more than what I read for you is written here.' And
then he goes ahead and he says the part in פנחס *Pinchas*,
meaning making it very clear that that is in the תורה Torah.
*Torah*, but I'm not reading it from the תורה Torah *Torah*. Okay?
So let's take a look. So—and we're going to talk about it.
Okay, וכל כך למה *V'chol kach lama*? Why does he have to
make this declaration? 'You should know that there's stuff here in the—in
the ספר *Sefer* that I'm not—you know, that—you know, there's more than—than
I've read.' So, like, what I'm saying now בעל פה *b'al peh*
is in the ספר *Sefer*. כדי שלא להוציא לעז על ספר תורה
Sefer Torah *Kedei shelo le-hotzi la'az al Sefer Torah*, so people should
not lead to a—you know, that they should not lead to rumoring
about the ספר תורה Sefer Torah *Sefer Torah* and say, 'Oh yeah,
he didn't read from פנחס *Pinchas*, probably is that that פרשה *parsha*
wasn't written in there. You know, probably there was a problem with
that פרשה *parsha* whatever.' No, it is in here, everything's okay with
the ספר *Sefer*, I'm just reading it בעל פה *b'al peh*. Now
we're going to discuss why he reads it בעל פה *b'al peh*.
ובעשור של חומש הפקודים *U've-asor shel Chumash HaPikudim*... he begins... בעל פה.
אמאי? Amai? Why? נגללו וניקרי. Niglolo venirkei.
Roll it up. Okay, so we sort of just a little bit
talked about jumping. So אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע אמר רב
Amar Rav Huna brei de'Rav Yehoshua amar Rav לפי שאין גוללים ספר
תורה בציבור. lefi she'ein golelim Sefer Torah batzibur. You don't roll it
up. Why do you not roll it up? Because it makes everybody
have to wait. So again it's quite
fascinating. Well we'll talk about that in a minute but again how
this סוגיא sugya doesn't reference the previous סוגיא sugya because the previous
סוגיא sugya implicitly had the same issue you don't jump waiting for
the guy to translate if you can do it within that time.
So anyway different way of framing a similar concern. Anyway you don't
roll it up in the ציבור tzibur in the middle of an
עלייה aliyah because it makes everybody wait. So the גמרא says מפני
כבוד הציבור. mipnei kvod hatzibur. By the way for all the this
concept of how is כבוד הציבור kvod hatzibur framed and what are
the issues around כבוד הציבור kvod hatzibur this is one of the
cases where it's labeled as that concern. ונייתי אחרינא וניקרי. Veneiti achrina
venikrei. Fine bring a second ספר תורה. Sefer Torah So רב הונא
בר יהודה אמר משום פגמו של ראשון. Rav Huna bar Yehuda amar
mishum pigmo shel rishon. No because then people will say ah you
had to bring a second one there was something wrong with the
first one you had to get out a second one. So we
don't want to look at that. ריש לקיש אמר Resh Lakish amar
one minute ריש לקיש אמר משום ברכה שאינה צריכה. Resh Lakish amar
mishum bracha she'eina tzricha. No because if you switch ספר תורה Sefer
Torah you'd have to make another ברכה. bracha. Now this is fascinating
because what other ברכה bracha would you have to make? The end
ברכות brachot again? The beginning ברכה bracha again? Who ever heard that
you make a beginning ברכה? bracha? This doesn't seem like it's the
standard institution of קריאת התורה. Kriat HaTorah. There aren't three עולים olim
he just gets up and reads. Now the final ברכה bracha he
does make is על התורה. al haTorah. Okay that we've seen that
he actually does make that ברכה bracha which is similar to the
final. But he makes seven other ברכות. brachot. So is this an
expansion of the framework of קריאת התורה? Kriat HaTorah? Did he make
the opening ברכה bracha of אשר בחר בנו? asher bachar banu? It
never said. When it's concerned here about the need to make another
ברכה bracha does it think that if you leave one ספר תורה
Sefer Torah you have to make all eight ברכות brachot and then
you're going to open up the next one and make all eight
ברכות? brachot? Is that what it's saying? Or is it saying no
actually there's an opening ברכה bracha here of אשר בחר בנו asher
bachar banu we didn't mention it and if you move to another
ספר תורה Sefer Torah he'll have to make another opening ברכה? bracha?
So it's not clear but it's just considered ברכה שאינה צריכה bracha
she'eina tzricha because
it's unnecessary. It's not לבטלה levatala but it's unnecessary. So again what's
fascinating here is A the assumption that switching a ספר תורה Sefer
Torah although there's no other עלייה aliyah there's nobody getting an עלייה
aliyah I mean if anywhere there's only one person getting an עלייה
aliyah the switching of the ספר תורה Sefer Torah. demands another ברכה
bracha because you have to give a blessing not just on the
reading as an abstract the blessing on the physical תורה that you're
reading from or that relates to the physical תורה. So the presence
of another ספר תורה Sefer Torah demands another ברכה. bracha. That's what's
fascinating number one. And number two is what do you call it
is the assumption that this is the possibility that this is somewhat
the structure of an עלייה aliyah and that actually maybe there's even
an opening ברכה bracha going on here that we did not reference.
Now of course when you find a טעות ta'ut in the ספר
תורה Sefer Torah and you switch it you don't make another ברכה.
bracha. So it raises yet but here at least there is this
assumption that it is. No let's just read more. It says okay
so he says משום ברכה שאינה צריכה. mishum bracha she'eina tzricha. ומי
חיישינן לפגמא? Umi chaishinan lepigma? Do we really concerned about a raising
a stigma on the first one? ואמר רבי יצחק נפחא ראש חודש
טבת שחל להיות בשבת. Ve'amar Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha Rosh Chodesh Tevet shechal
lihyot beShabbat. If it's Rosh Chodesh Tevet on Shabbat right and it's
חנוכה Chanukah מביאין שלשה תורות mevi'in shlosha Torot וקורא אחת בענינו של
יום vekorei achat be'inyano shel yom
one you read whatever the Shabbat פרשה is ואחת של ראש חודש
ve'achat shel Rosh Chodesh ואחת של חנוכה. ve'achat shel Chanukah. So you
have three ספרי תורות. Sifrei Torot. תלתא גברי בתלתא סיפרי ליכא פגמא.
Tlata gavrei betlata sifrei leika pegama.
Three different people with three ספרי תורה Sifrei Torah each one gets
a separate עלייה aliyah there's no פגם. pegam. You know you didn't
abandon one in the middle of an עלייה. aliyah. So each one
gets their separate ספר that's not a problem similar to issues discussed
before about jumping around in the reading of תענית. Taanit. חד גברא
בתרי סיפרי איכא פגמא. Chad gavra bitrei sifrei ika pegama. But have
one person in the middle of his קריאה kria go to another
ספר there is a concern of stigmatizing. And this is an issue
that comes up in various contexts when problems might come up in
a ספר תורה Sefer Torah. and so on. So again though the
upshot is so fine that explains why you didn't scroll A you
don't scroll you don't want to make people wait you don't move
a ספר תורה. sefer torah. But again the question that we're left
with is first the reality that you would that would demand another
ברכה bracha to switch a ספר תורה sefer torah and two the
question about how much is this an expansion of the general structure
of an עלייה. aliyah. How much was there an opening ברכה bracha
as well is not said but it's certainly left us wondering. Okay
very quick 'cause we're like way behind.
You make a point. So one thing is it's interesting to think
the ברכה שאינה צריכה bracha she'eina tzricha seems to be going on
all of both ספרי תורה Sifrei Torah for example Sephardic you know
that you do a קדיש Kaddish on both ספרי תורה Sifrei Torah
if there's two
was it two or three? Well קדיש Kaddish is not the same
as a ברכה. bracha.
And then the other thing is so why don't they do just
like what they have with סוטה? Sotah? Where they had sort of
a מגילה Megillah they had it over there. So just have like
a parchment that has it all on one and then you don't
have to worry about anything.
No because it's not like the מגילה. Megillah. The whole point here
is that it's an act of קריאת התורה. Kriat HaTorah. It is
similar to the whole institute rabbinic institution of קריאת התורה Kriat HaTorah
to relate to the actual גוף ספר תורה. guf Sefer Torah. And
of course yeah I mean the whole and that's the thing to
remember again they're making it they're having a show experience they're getting
the ראש הכנסת. Rosh HaKnesset. So that's the question of... How much
is this really that institution of a classic קריאת
התורה,
Kriat
HaTorah, yeah.
Odd to you that the verb is to read when he's not
reading?
What do you mean?
קורא בעל פה. Korei b'al peh. Yeah, but he's reciting a verse,
he's reciting something that's written. Yeah, yeah, because קורא korei is also
מקרא, Mikra, it's the recital. No, no, no, but it's because it's
מקרא, Mikra, it relates to the recitation of a biblical verse.
I understand, but the word קורא korei relates to מקרא. Mikra. You
would not say he's קורא korei from ספר המכבים Sefer HaMaccabim or
he's קורא korei from the משנה, Mishnah, okay? I don't think you
would. Because it's מקרא Mikra you use that verb. Okay. ומברך עליה
שמונה ברכות. Umivarech aleha shmoneh brachot. And so eight blessings. תנו רבנן.
Tanu rabanan. על התורה, Al haTorah, so one ברכה bracha is על
התורה, al haTorah, כדרך שמברכים בבית הכנסת, kederech shemevarchim bebeit haknesset, like
you say at the end of an עליה, aliyah, right? אשר נתן
לנו תורת אמת, asher natan lanu Torat emet, right, the end ברכה
bracha of an עליה. aliyah. Again, we mentioned the question of is
there a beginning one. Okay. על עבודה ועל ההודאה ועל מחילת העוון,
Al avodah ve'al hahoda'ah ve'al mechilat ha'avon, כתקנה, kitknah, those three ברכות
brachot are like the standard. What do you mean standard? No, because
we actually have a ברכה bracha on עבודה, avodah, רצה. Retzei. Now,
right? So we end המחזיר שכינתו לציון. hamachazir schinato leTzion. But רש"י
Rashi says you would end like we end by when we do
the ברכת כהנים, birkat kohanim, שאותך לבדך ביראה נעבוד, she'otecha levadecha beyirah
na'avod, which could reflect how you say a ברכה bracha of accept
our sacrifices at a time when there is a בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. So that's עבודה. avodah. What do we say, what's after רצה?
Retzei? What ברכה bracha in שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei after רצה? Retzei?
מודים, Modim, ועל ההודאה. ve'al hahoda'ah. מודים אנחנו לך. Modim anachnu lach.
Okay, that's the מודים Modim after God accepts the sacrifices you give
thanks.
Okay. ועל מחילת העוון, Ve'al mechilat ha'avon, what, where's that? Well there's
a ברכה bracha on יום כיפור Yom Kippur about
מחילת העוון. mechilat ha'avon. מוחל לעוונותינו ולעוונות עמו בית ישראל מעביר אשמותינו
בכל שנה ושנה מלך מוחל וסולח. Mochel la'avonoteinu vela'avonot amo beit Yisrael
ma'avir ashmoteinu bechol shanah veshanah melech mochel vesole'ach. That ברכה bracha is
what the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol makes now after the עבודה avodah
is finished. ועל המקדש בפני עצמו ועל הכהנים בפני עצמם ועל ישראל
בפני עצמם ועל שאר תפילה. Ve'al haMikdash bifnei atzmo ve'al hakohanim bifnei
atzmam ve'al Yisrael bifnei atzmam ve'al shear tfillah. And it doesn't elaborate
what those ברכות brachot are. We mentioned when we read the משנה
Mishnah how רש"י, Rashi the text רש"י Rashi gives is ירושלמי Yerushalmi
that also gives the text for those ברכות. brachot. By the way,
this listing left out ירושלים Yerushalayim because with ירושלים Yerushalayim there's nine.
And other versions of the משנה Mishnah we read earlier also do
not have ירושלים Yerushalayim and therefore you have eight. Okay. תנו רבנן.
Tanu rabanan. So what is this שאר תפילה, shear tfillah, this last
one is very generic. So here's what, here's what it is. רינה
תחינה בקשה מלפניך, Rinah tchinah bakashah milfanecha, God, a song, a supplication,
a request from you, על עמך ישראל שצריכים להיוושע, al amcha Yisrael
shetzrichim lehivashea, your nation Israel needs to be
saved, salvation, and presumably you then elaborate on it. וחותם בשומע תפילה,
Vechotem beshome'a tfillah, which is what we actually say before רצה. Retzei.
Okay, but you know here the focus starts with the עבודה. avodah.
So the רצה, Retzei, which is about the קרבנות, korbanot, comes first.
Then the שומע תפילה shome'a tfillah is the whole generic תפילה, tfillah,
everything that we ask for. Listen to your people Israel when they
cry out. שומע תפילה Shome'a tfillah is quite ironic, right? We have
spent all of this שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei asking for specific things
and then we ask for listen to what we asked for, right?
So it could be to say please accept our requests and listen
to what we said before, but it also could just be like
the catch-all, there's so many other things that we need, please always
be listening to the things that we request and that we need
even if we can't articulate them and so on. So שומע תפילה
shome'a tfillah is the big generic תפילה. tfillah.
So again, it's interesting to think as we've been talking about about
the shift between מקדש Mikdash and תפילה. tfillah. מקדש, Mikdash, you know
sort of the ritual of קרבנות korbanot and תשובה. teshuvah. So here
you have a grafting of the בית כנסת, Beit Knesset, the קריאת
התורה Kriat HaTorah on it, but with that בית כנסת Beit Knesset
reality you have these ברכות, brachot, right? And these ברכות, brachot, so
according to the תוספות ישנים Tosafot Yeshanim you might remember, he said
the whole reason you do the major reason you do the קריאת
התורה Kriat HaTorah is in order to give ברכות brachot on the
עבודה. avodah. So to frame everything that came before, you know with
these words, with this תפילה, tfillah, with these ברכות, brachot, all of
this profound ritual. Or you know, but here it's interesting to just
notice the reversal of the order. We start with שומע תפילה shome'a
tfillah and then do רצה. Retzei. Here it starts with רצה Retzei
and מודים Modim because it starts with קרבנות korbanot and then it
shifts to the generic תפילה, tfillah, anything that your people need. Yes?
Is it a מודים דרבנן? Modim derabanan?
Which of the two מודים Modims is it? I don't know. Is
that what you're asking?
Is it the מודים דרבנן Modim derabanan is grafting all that? Is
bringing all that together?
Is it the what of the רבנן? rabanan?
The מודים דרבנן. Modim derabanan.
The
references to the חצרות chatzerot and the מקדש. Mikdash.
Oh, that's what you mean, that the מודים דרבנן Modim derabanan makes
a reference to all of those?
Could be. I mean I see that more powerfully in the רצה,
Retzei, but right, ואישי ישראל ותפילתם, ve'ishei Yisrael utfillatam, right, that it
mentions אישי ישראל ishei Yisrael which is also very abstractly referring to
the קרבנות korbanot and moves into תפילתם. tfillatam.
So but yeah, the מודים Modim too, I hadn't thought about that
but you're right, it also is present in the מודים. Modim.
Okay. So תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. Okay, so okay. ואחר כך כל
אחד ואחד מביא ספר תורה מביתו, Ve'achar kach kol echad ve'echad mevi
sefer Torah mibeito, afterwards everybody brings a ספר תורה sefer torah from
their house, וקורא בו, vekorei bo, and reads from the ספר תורה.
sefer torah, Or after they've heard the כהן גדול's kohen gadol reading
of the ספר תורה. So the whole idea of like following around
with your own מגילה megillah during קריאת מגילה krias megillah is an
old practice, כדי להראות חזותו לרבים kedei leharot chazuto larabim to show
its appearance to the masses. Now what is going on there? First
of all, aren't they carrying? So רש"י Rashi says they brought it
all from ערב יום טוב, erev yom tov, from ערב יום כיפור.
erev yom kippur. The מהרש"א Maharsha says I don't know what, or
רש"ש, Rashash, רש"ש, Rashash, yeah I know it doesn't fit the language.
The רש"ש Rashash says why you have to say that? There's other
גמרות gemaras that say that ירושלים Yerushalayim was a walled city because
it's a walled city, you're it's an עירוב, eruv, you're allowed to
carry it, so no big deal, ירושלים. Yerushalayim. But what is this
כדי להראות חזותו? kedei leharot chazuto? So רש"י Rashi says oh because
there's this whole idea of נוי מצוה noy mitzvah and beautifying the
מצוה mitzvah and you want to show everybody what a beautiful ספר
תורה you have and beautiful קלף. klaf. Yeah but like why now?
Like what's the... I mean because everybody's around, it's a big gathering,
you want to show everybody look at this gorgeous ספר תורה I
brought to read along with.
I don't exactly get that כדי להראות חזותו לרבים. kedei leharot chazuto
larabim. Again the only thing that I will again suggest is maybe
it's a you know with all of this focus on the קרבנות
korbanot and that is the very visual and powerful experience, it's also
like a reorienting to תורה, you know and again sort of the
shift again thinking about the קרבנות korbanot versus the center of you
know is the center of Judaism the מקדש Mikdash or is it
תורה? You know so maybe there's a little hint to that but
that might be a little
speculative. Whoever had brought,
okay. הרואה כהן גדול לא מפני שאינו רשאי. Haroeh Kohen Gadol lo
mipnei she'eino rashai. If you see the כהן גדול kohen gadol reading
the תורה, you don't see the things being burned, the carcasses, not
you're not allowed but you can't do two things at once. So
מהרש"א Maharsha says פשיטא, pshita, obviously there's not that you're not allowed.
Why would I say you're not allowed to go from one to
the other? No מהו דתימא mahu deiteima כדריש לקיש, k'deReish Lakish, maybe
it's like ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, דאמר ריש לקיש אין מעבירין על
המצות. d'amar Reish Lakish ein maavirin al hamitzvot. If you're in begin
one מצוה, mitzvah, you encounter one מצוה, mitzvah, you can't leave it
to do another. So so maybe if you're doing one thing, you're
present in one of these experiences, you can't leave it to be
present and you know be in the other one. So רש"י says
but you're only just present, what מצוה mitzvah are you doing? You're
not actually reading the תורה. ומאי מצוה, umai mitzvah, what is the
מצוה mitzvah you're doing? ברוב עם הדרת מלך, berov am hadrat melech,
you're being part of the masses that are assembled. That's part of
what it means to participate. You can participate, you know they only
serve they also serve those who only stand and wait. No that's
a different guy. But anyway participating is also like being a presence
you know at when when an event is taking place. So קא
משמע לן kamashmalan that that would not be a problem you actually
would be allowed to shift. Now why would you be allowed to
shift? So רש"י says it's a great הוה אמינא. havamina. רש"י says
קא משמע לן דלאו מעביר הוא מאחר שאינו עוסק בה. kamashmalan delav
maavir hu meachar sheino osek bah. So that means that we don't
we discount your presence, as if you don't really matter, you're not
really participating, you're just watching, you're just hearing. No we do have
an idea of ברוב עם הדרת מלך. berov am hadrat melech. So
even though there's an idea of a degree of participation, it's not
direct participation, you still are allowed to leave and go to another
one. Okay but I do think that the idea it's talking about
here is how much even if you're not the actor, you're just
in the שול shul when the דאוונען davening is going on, you're
present when something is going on, how much are you also seen
as a participant in the events that are happening, I think is
a powerful idea here. Maybe not so much that you can't move
from one to the other, but to a degree that it's ברוב
עם הדרת מלך berov am hadrat melech and you add and you
create the experience, yes. Okay moving on now continuing the עבודה. avodah.
He read some of the ספר תורה, which is sort of the
one thing that is like a the שול shul experience grafted in,
not in the פסוקים pesukim. at all. Now we get back to
the types of stuff that's in the פסוקים. pesukim בבגדי בוץ קורא,
bevigdei butz korei, if he was reading in his linen garments, his
בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehuna, קידש, kideish, now he has to take them
off. So now we go through the process of removing the garments,
which requires washing the hands, and then dressing getting into the new
garments. קידש ידיו ורגליו, kideish yadav veraglav, he washes his hands for
taking before he takes off his old ones, for the end of
the sort of wearing of those of that of those garments. Then
פשט, pashat, he strips, ירד וטבל, yarad v'taval, he goes to the
מקוה, mikvah, עלה, ala, he gets out of the מקוה, mikvah, ונסתפג,
venishtagev, he dries himself off, הביאו לו בגדי זהב, heivi lo bigdei
zahav, now they he's done with the major עבודה avodah of יום
כיפור Yom Kippur of בגדי לבן, bigdei lavan, now he wears his
standard garments which have gold in them, ולבש, velavash, and he dresses
and he robed, he puts them on. וקידש ידיו ורגליו, vekideish yadav
veraglav, and he washed his hands because again according to the משנה
Mishnah the hand washing is done only when the garments are on.
So when you put on the new garments you wash, before you
take them off you wash, and then you wash. Okay ויצא, veyatza,
then goes out, ועשה אילו ואת איל העם, veasah eilo veet eil
ha'am, right which is almost a quote from the פסוקים. psukim ויצא
ועשה, veyatza veasah, you know he goes out of ויצא veyatza in
the פסוקים psukim is he's יצא yatza from the היכל. Heichal. But
here ויצא veyatza is wherever he was reading it, I don't know,
the עזרת נשים, Ezras Nashim, now he goes and he does the
ram, because you'll remember in אחרי מות, Acharei Mos, the the תורה
like mentions it just very quickly in passing, there's no big description
of what's being done. Yes now just go ahead and do the
rams. But together with the goat and the calf and the ox
came each one was coupled with a ram and it was לעולה.
l'olah. So ואיל אחד לעולה. v'ayil echad l'olah. Okay so now he
does brings those two עולות, olot, his and the one for that
was that was together with his ox and the one that was
together with the people's goat.
ואת שבעת כבשים תמימים בני שנה ve'et shivat kevasim temimim bnei shana
and the seven pure
lambs again. meaning this is what's written in אמור. Emor. Now he
also brings the מוסף. Mussaf. The עבודת יום כיפור Avodas Yom Kippur
is not the מוסף. Mussaf. Now he brings the מוסף. Mussaf. דברי
רבי אליעזר. Divrei Rabbi Eliezer. That's what Rabbi Eliezer says. רבי עקיבא
אומר אם תמיד של שחר היו קרבים. Rabbi Akiva omer im tamid
shel shachar hayu krevin. No, the מוסף Mussaf was brought with the
תמיד של שחר. tamid shel shachar. It took place before the עבודת
יום כיפור. Avodas Yom Kippur. Okay. Interesting question, when do we say
in the דאבנינג davening the מוסף, Mussaf, the פסוקים of the מוסף?
Mussaf? After the עבודה avodah or before? Before? No, I think we
say—really? I thought we said—no, because we say it
in—no, no, no, when do we say the פסוקים of the מוסף
Mussaf in during מוסף Mussaf of שמונה עשרה? shmoneh esrei?
During—no, in חזרת הש"ץ chazaras hashatz because only חזרת הש"ץ chazaras hashatz
has the עבודה. avodah.
Well, the עלינו aleinu immediately follows the ברכה bracha
of—not
the—yeah.
Alright,
you can do—you can do that as an assignment for everybody. Is
it before the עבודה? avodah? Okay, I don't remember.
The עבודה avodah ends with סליחות.
selichos. Right, right, right,
right.
And then—and then—aha. Okay.
Alright, so you'll check—oh yeah, it depends when you do אמיץ כוח.
amitz koach. Alright, so anyway, so people can go ahead and check.
I don't remember. רבי עקיבא אומר עם תמיד של שחר היו קרבים.
Rabbi Akiva omer im tamid shel shachar hayu krevin. So he says
the מוסף Mussaf would be with the תמיד של שחר. tamid shel
shachar. ופר עולה ושעיר הנעשה
בחוץ. U'par olah v'se'ir hana'aseh bachutz. Now how about—we're not done because
part of the מוסף Mussaf is not just the seven lambs. Together
with the מוסף Mussaf is an ox for an עולה olah and
a goat which is here described as done outside because there's these
goats—the goat of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, the blood was on inside,
but the classic goat that is brought with every מוסף Mussaf is
a שעיר לחטאת, se'ir l'chatas, a goat לחתאת, l'chatas, and that's done
obviously on the outer מזבח. mizbe'ach. So how about these two which
are the remnant of the מוסף? Mussaf? When do you do this?
בחוץ היו קרבים עם תמיד של בין הערביים. Bachutz hayu krevin im
tamid shel bein ha'arbayim. So according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, it
would—those would be brought with the afternoon. So according to רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, תמיד, tamid, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would have that it's
linked with the תמיד tamid and not with these other stuff of
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So according to—we don't really know where it
is. This is gonna get confusing. I might have to make a
chart so that I won't be able to—on שבת. But anyway, but
you have here, you have the תמיד, tamid, right? That's when he's
wearing the first בגדים. bgadim. Then you have the עבודת יום כיפור,
Avodas Yom Kippur, right? This is זהב, zahav, לבן, lavan, right? זהב.
zahav. Then you have this, which starts with אילו ואיל העם, aylo
v'ayil ha'am, which is the end of the עבודת יום כיפור. Avodas
Yom Kippur. Okay? Then you again you have the לבן, lavan, which
is the הוצאת הכף. hotza'as hakaf. And
then you have the final זהב, zahav, which is the—which is the
תמיד של בין הערביים. tamid shel bein ha'arbayim.
Okay. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you would do part one
of the מוסף Mussaf here,
מוסף Mussaf one.
Why do we do it so early?
And whatever, we'll talk in the גמרא. And part two of the
מוסף Mussaf here, right? He says with the תמיד של בין הערביים.
tamid shel bein ha'arbayim. That's when you do the ox and the—and
the goat. So the only thing you do here, even though you're
wearing the gold garments, is basically the remainder of the עבודת יום
כיפור. Avodas Yom Kippur. So for him, he separates out all the
parts of the מוסף Mussaf to give this its total focus. You
know, this is just יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, even the לבן—even lavan
the בגדי זהב bigdei zahav is just the ram, the אילו ואיל
העם aylo v'ayil ha'am that's connected to the עבודת יום כיפור, Avodas
Yom Kippur, as opposed to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that had part
of the מוסף Mussaf being done here together with this. Alright? Pretty
clear? More or less? As clear as it's gonna get. Okay. So,
alright.
קידש ידיו ורגליו, Kiddesh yadav v'raglav, so he's done with whatever he
does now wear in the second wearing of the gold garments, minimally,
of course, the ram, the—his אילו ואיל העם. aylo v'ayil ha'am. פשט
וירד וטבל עלה ונסתפג והביאו לו בגדי לבן. Pashat v'yarad v'taval alah
v'nistapeg v'hevi'u lo bigdei lavan. He does the washing, the טבילה, tvilah,
and he gets dressed in now the white garments again. לבש וקידש
ידיו ורגליו, lavash v'kiddesh yadav v'raglav, dresses, washes his hands. נכנס להוציא
את הכף ואת המחתה. Nichnas l'hotzi es hakaf v'es hamachta. The only
thing he does now in the second wearing of the white garments
is the taking out of the fire pan
and of the—of the spoon, thank you, that had the incense. קידש
ידיו ורגליו פשט וירד וטבל עלה ונסתפג והביאו לו בגדי זהב, Kiddesh
yadav v'raglav pashat v'yarad v'taval alah v'nistapeg v'hevi'u lo bigdei zahav, goes
to the whole washing again, the third wearing of the gold garments.
Okay. ולבש וקידש ידיו ורגליו ונכנס להקטיר קטורת של בין הערביים ולהטיב
את הנרות. V'lavash v'kiddesh yadav v'raglav v'nichnas l'haktir ktoret shel bein ha'arbayim
u'l'hativ es hanerot. And he does—it's interesting, it doesn't mention the תמיד
של בין הערביים, tamid shel bein ha'arbayim, which is part of this,
that you would think is the biggest thing, but the other things
that go with the afternoon תמיד tamid also, which is the afternoon
קטורת ktoret and the—and the lighting of the נרות. nerot. קידש ידיו
ורגליו ופשט, Kiddesh yadav v'raglav u'fashat, and he now does it the
final time. He does not go back to the מקווה mikvah because
now he's done with the entire עבודה, avodah, so he just does
one last washing of the hands. הביאו לו בגדי עצמו, Hevi'u lo
bigdei atzmo, and then he gets his own street clothes, ולבשן, v'lavashan,
and he wears them. ומלווין אותו עד ביתו, U'melavin oso ad beiso,
and there would be a whole retinue that would accompany him to
his house. ויום טוב היה עושה לאוהביו, V'yom tov haya oseh l'ohavav,
and he would make a יום טוב Yom tov for his—for his
friends, בשעה שיצא בשלום מן הקודש. b'shaa sheyatza b'shalom min hakodesh. So
and when he left with peace What? Yeah, ברוך השם *Baruch Hashem*.
Okay. איבעיא להו *Ibeiya lehu*. We'll finish it when we're done with
the שביעי *shevi'i* פרק *perek*. איבעיא להו היכי קאמר *Ibeiya lehu heichi
k'amar*. Now, אם תמיד tamid של שחר *im tamid shel shachar* now
first of all it says I just have a textual question in
Rabbi Eliezer when he says right I'm sorry when Rabbi Akiva says
that that the seven lambs were with the morning תמיד tamid. *tamid*
ופר העולה ושעיר הנעשה בחוץ *u'par ha'olah ve'se'ir hana'aseh bachutz* were with
the afternoon it says there's an ambiguity what whether it says and
the ox which part of that sentence it's going on. היכי קאמר
*Heichi k'amar*. What are you saying? אם תמיד של שחר היו קרבים
ופר העולה ושעיר הנעשה בחוץ עם תמיד של בין הערבים *Im tamid
shel shachar hayu k'revim u'par ha'olah ve'se'ir hana'aseh bachutz im tamid shel
bein ha'arbayim*. So the seven lambs the first half of the מוסף
musaf *musaf* was the morning and the ox and the goat the
second part of the מוסף musaf *musaf* was the afternoon. או דילמא
הכי קאמר *O dilma hachi k'amar* maybe this is what you're saying:
אם תמיד של שחר היו קרבים ופר העולה בהדייהו *im tamid shel
shachar hayu k'revim u'par ha'olah behadayhu*. The seven lambs plus the ox
were with the morning were with the morning תמיד *tamid* ושעיר הנעשה
בחוץ עם תמיד של בין הערבים *ve'se'ir hana'aseh bachutz im tamid shel
bein ha'arbayim* and maybe only the goat was with the where do
you put the period in that sentence maybe only the goat was
with the afternoon. So A we're not really clear on Rabbi Akiva
there's a little ambiguity though that's not really much of an ambiguity
as תוספות *Tosafos* points out because of the plural because of the
plural of the verb anyway that's one ambiguity. ותו *Ve'tu* but now
we have a real uncertainty in terms of Rabbi Eliezer. לפר העולה
*Le'par ha'olah* ל-Rabbi Eliezer *le-Rabbi Eliezer* דשרי *de'sharei* Rabbi Eliezer mentioned the
seven lambs he said right Rabbi Eliezer had the מוסף musaf *musaf*
go here according to Rabbi Eliezer you
have the purple is Rabbi Akiva the blue is Rabbi Eliezer so
according to Rabbi Eliezer you have מוסף musaf *musaf* one here the
seven כבשים *k'vasim*.
Okay he never told you where you do מוסף musaf *musaf* two
where you do the second part of the מוסף musaf *musaf* where
you do the ox and the the ox and the goat. ותו
פר העולה ל-Rabbi Eliezer דשרי אימת עביד לה *Ve'tu par ha'olah le-Rabbi
Eliezer de'sharei eimat avid leh* where was the ox? רש"י *Rashi* says
it also means where was the goat also you never he didn't
tell us where you do that. ותו *Ve'tu* and in addition בין
*bein* Rabbi Eliezer בין *bein* Rabbi Akiva אימורי חטאת chatat אימת עביד
להו *imurei chatat eimat avid lehu*
how about the the you know inwards and the intestines of the
פר ושעיר *par ve'se'ir* remember he cut up the animal he took
out the intestines he sent the carcasses to be burned. When does
he when does he put those intestines on the altar? So we
don't have a clear description of every detail of what is going
on. אמר רבא *Amar Rava* so said Rava לא משכחת לה מתקנתא
*lo mashchachat leh metakanta* you could not find this sort of fix
meaning clearly delineated what everything where everything happens you won't find it
in a משנה *Mishnah*. The משנה *Mishnah* does not spell out all
of the details. אלא *Ella* if you want to find a clear
delineation it's או *o* Rabbi Eliezer דתנא דבי שמואל *de'tana de'vei Shmuel*
either the version of Rabbi Eliezer in a ברייתא *Baraisa* from the
house of שמואל *Shmuel* and I'm going to warn you ahead of
time this Rabbi Eliezer is not the same position as the Rabbi
Eliezer of the משנה *Mishnah* so don't ask me why it don't
ask me about the contradiction it's a different version of Rabbi Eliezer.
There it's spelled out. או *O* ל-Rabbi Akiva *le-Rabbi Akiva* כדתוספתא *k'de-Tosefta*
or a Rabbi Akiva as it's found in the תוספתא *Tosefta*. But
in the משנה *Mishnah* there's a lot of ambiguity. Now let's see
what these two positions are in the ברייתא *Baraisa*. דתנא דבי שמואל
*De'tana de'vei Shmuel* Rabbi Eliezer
אומר
יצא ועשה אילו ואיל העם ואימורי חטאת chatat *omer yatzah ve'asah eilo
ve'eil ha'am ve'imurei chatat*
so according to this version of Rabbi Eliezer here's you did the
אימורים eimurim, *imurim* with the איל eil, *ayil* אבל פר העולה ושבעה
כבשים ושעיר
הנעשה בחוץ עם תמיד של בין הערבים *aval
par ha'olah ve'shiva k'vasim ve'se'ir hana'aseh bachutz im tamid shel bein ha'arbayim*.
So according
to this Rabbi
Eliezer
of the תוספתא *Tosefta* of the ברייתא *Baraisa* Rabbi Eliezer of
I don't know שמואל *Shmuel* is here you do you do the
אימורי פר ושעיר *imurei par ve'se'ir*. So by the way it's still
nice because according to this version as well like Rabbi Akiva the
only thing being done here is pure יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom
Kippur* just only the אימורי פר ושעיר *imurei par ve'se'ir* and then
here in the final בגדי זהב *bigdei zahav* according to this you
would do the entire מוסף musaf *musaf*.
All of the מוסף musaf *musaf*.
Okay so that's a version of Rabbi Eliezer עם תמיד של בין
הערבים *im
tamid shel bein ha'arbayim*
together with the תמיד של בין הערבים *tamid shel bein ha'arbayim* yeah
before but okay אבל פר העולה ושבעה כבשים ושעיר הנעשה בחוץ עם
תמיד של בין הערבים *aval par ha'olah ve'shiva k'vasim ve'se'ir hana'aseh bachutz
im tamid shel bein ha'arbayim*. Rabbi Akiva דתוספתא *de-Tosefta* what's Akiva the
תוספתא *Tosefta*? מאי היא דתניא *Mai hi de'tanya* Rabbi Akiva אומר פר
העולה ושבעה כבשים עם תמיד של שחר היו קרבים *omer par ha'olah
ve'shiva k'vasim im tamid shel shachar hayu k'revim* okay
that he made that according to the Rabbi Akiva the תוספתא *Tosefta*
it's not just the it's not just the seven כבשים *k'vasim* it
also includes a פר *par* so now was just left the שעיר
sa'ir *se'ir* okay just most of the מוסף musaf *musaf* okay שנאמר
מלבד עולת הבקר אשר לעולת התמיד *she'ne'emar milvad olas haboker asher le'olas
hatamid*
in addition to the morning sacrifice which according to Rabbi Akiva means
the מוסף *musaf* is always brought in the same context. As the
morning תמיד. That's the פסוק pasuk, that he says that explains why
we're bringing the מוסף with the תמיד before the עבודה, avodah, not
after the עבודה. avodah. ואחר כך עבודת היום, ve'achar kach avodat hayom,
then you do the עבודה avodah of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, ואחר
כך שעיר הנעשה בחוץ, ve'achar kach sa'ir hana'aseh bachutz,
then you do the goat, שנאמר שעיר עזים אחד חטאת מלבד חטאת
הכפורים. shene'emar sa'ir izim echad chatat milvad chatat hakippurim.
So because the goat is other than the חטאת chatat, of the
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, which means after the חטאת of יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur ואחר כך אילו ואיל העם, ve'achar kach eilo ve'eil ha'am,
then you do the ram, ואחר כך אימורי חטאת, ve'achar kach eimurei
chatat, then you do the אימורים, eimurim, ואחר כך תמיד של בין
הערביים, ve'achar kach tamid shel bein ha'arbayim, and then you do the
תמיד של בין הערביים. tamid shel bein ha'arbayim. So according to this,
here you've done, according to this version of Rabbi Akiva, you've done
pretty much the entire מוסף because it says, and this is what
we'll end, על עולת התמיד, al olat hatamid,
that's the פסוק, pasuk so מוסף goes with the תמיד. Then here
he says you do the,
here what he says you do is you do the first thing
you do is the שעיר sa'ir of the מוסף because it says
מלבד חטאת הכפורים. milvad chatat hakippurim. So remember the עבודת יום הכפורים
avodat Yom hakippurim had a שעיר sa'ir for חטאת, right, the people's
שעיר sa'ir that was inside? Yes. So since the פסוק says you
do this שעיר sa'ir for the מוסף on יום כיפור in addition
to this שעיר sa'ir that's the עבודה, avodah, so for Rabbi Akiva,
he's very focused on whenever these things are linked, they come together.
So the מוסף is linked to עולה, olah, come together. This שעיר
sa'ir, is said in addition to this שעיר, sa'ir so the very
next thing you do after this שעיר sa'ir is this. Okay, then,
then he says what do you do? Then you do
the איל, that's the other big fat, right, that's the end of
the עבודה, avodah, and then the אימורים, because that's like the wrap-up
of the עבודה. avodah. And after, and then finally he says you
do the ואחר כך אימורי חטאת ואחר כך, ve'achar kach eimurei chatat
ve'achar kach, and then way over here you do the תמיד של
בין הערביים. tamid shel bein ha'arbayim. Okay, so according to Rabbi Akiva
basically pretty much all of the מוסף is up here except for
the שעיר and then you finish it. And according to these other
versions, you don't do the מוסף up front, you do the מוסף
after and maybe divide them up into different sections. So I'm sure
that was super clear and tomorrow
we will wrap up what their different positions are, what their different
reasons are.